[Music]
This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
se-radio.net. SE Radio is brought to you
by the ITE computer society and by it
eles software magazine online at
[Music]
computer.org/software. Welcome to
Software Engineering Radio. I'm your
host Jeff Doolittle. This episode will
explore how to balance coupling and
software design. Coupling and the
related topic of complexity have come up
in previous episodes. For example, in
episode 638, Nick Tune and Jean George
Parin talked about architecture
modernization. In episode 637, the topic
came up when Steve Smith shared his
views on software quality. And in
episode 520, John Osterhout discussed
his book, A Philosophy of Software
Design, which also explores topics
related to coupling and complexity. And
today we'll be talking with Vlad Konov
about his book, Balancing Coupling in
Software Design. Vlad is a software
architect with extensive industry
experience working for companies large
and small in roles ranging from web
master to chief architect. Currently, he
helps companies to make sense of their
business domains, untangle monoliths,
and tackle complex architectural
challenges. In 2021, Vlad authored
Learning Domain Driven Design, followed
by the publication of his second book,
Balancing Coupling in Software Design in
2024. He is also a public speaker
presenting on topics such as domain
driven design, distributed systems, and
software architecture. Vlad, welcome to
the show. Hi Jeff, thank you so much for
having me. Really glad you're here. So,
let's kick it off. A lot of ink has been
spilled on the subject of coupling. What
compelled you to write a book on the
subject? Well, in my opinion, that's not
enough ink that has been spelled on this
topic and I had to spell much more. Now,
seriously, if you look at most of
software engineer and software
architecture books, you will find a
section dedicated to coupling, maybe
even a chapter, at most a chapter. So, I
decided that this topic is way too
important and I'll do the opposite. I'll
dedicate a whole book to coupling and
there will be one chapter about
everything else. Great. So you mentioned
in the book and as we've spoken
previously the idea of complexity in the
context of coupling and this comes up a
lot in some of those previous episodes
as well and in some of the books you
mentioned. Do you have a different
perspective on how complexity and
coupling relate to each other or maybe
the definitions of those terms? Yeah, of
course. Now when a software engineer
tries to deal with coupling the goal is
usually to address complexity. So we are
here for that goal to manage complexity
of our business domain and to manage the
complexity of the software solution that
we are designing. Of course, what we
want to do is to manage it to make sure
that we can control how that complexity
is going to affect the design and of
course to minimize the accidental
complexity that our design introduces to
the system. So that's my overall goal
for building that framework for managing
coupling. In a sense, it's a way to
manage complexity through the management
of coupling. Now in order to manage
complexity, we need to make sure that we
understand what is complexity and that
we have an agreement between each other
on how we're going to define complexity,
how we're going to work with it. And
there are many different some of them
are complicated definitions of
complexity. The one that I prefer to use
when working on software design comes
from the canvan framework from Dave
Snowden. And this canvan is a decision
making framework. It's a framework that
helps you to make decisions in different
situations. Basically what Dave says is
that complexity is a function of an
action and the result of this action. If
you're working on a system and you want
to do something, let's say you want to
introduce a change and you know exactly
what's going to happen following that
change. Well, that's not a complex
system. you are dealing with something
that is clear or obvious. If on the
other hand you don't know what's going
to happen but there is someone some
external expert that you can consult and
that person will tell you hey if you do
this that thing is going to happen again
that's not complexity in the language of
canvan it's called a complicated domain
or a complicated system now if on the
other hand you want to make a change and
the only way of truly finding out the
outcome of that action is to make the
change and then they observe the results
or in other words the outcome can only
be deduced in retrospect then you're
dealing with complexity in our domain of
software engineering let's say that you
are working on a project that is
designed as a big ball of mud or rather
not designed at all right and you want
to make a change the only way to find
out what's going to happen is to make
the change observe the results hopefully
observe the results in development
environment or in testing environment
not in production
Well, that's complexity. Or maybe you
think that you know what's going to
happen, but then you deploy it to
production and let's say a month later
you discover that there is something
else that's going to happen. Again,
that's complexity. That's something that
we want to avoid. So the goal of my
framework for managing coupling is to
avoid such situations to take us from
that retrospective knowledge of what's
going to happen all the way back to the
clear domain where we have at least some
understanding of what's going to happen
if we do something. So to dive a little
bit more into that, it sounds like what
you're saying is just because something
exists in a complex domain, it doesn't
mean that we can't find ways to maybe
move it into those other domains over
time using various techniques. Yeah,
exactly. And here it's worth to
differentiate between two types of
complexities. One is the essential
complexity of the business domain. Say
you're working on a medical system or a
financial system. That's not an easy
system to build, right? It's complex.
That business domain is complex. There
is nothing you can do about it. However,
the design itself that you are
architecting, that's something that you
can control. And here you can either
introduce accidental complexity or you
can manage the complexity of the
business domain. And instead of
accidental complexity, design a modular
solution. a solution that is going to be
much more predictable and much easier to
change in the future. And you just
brought in a new word which I think is
great. So we've talked about complexity
and coupling and now you brought in the
word modularity and that's another word
of which much ink has also been spilled
and much radio time or podcast time has
been spent. But talk a little bit about
the relationship between those three
concepts and I think that'll set us up
for where we want to take the rest of
this conversation. Yeah, sure. So again,
not enough ink. Not enough. Fair. Great.
Yeah. So first of all, we have that
agreement that we want to avoid
complexity. The second agreement we have
to make is what we want to achieve. And
of course that's modularity. So we can
treat modularity as the opposite of
complexity. Complexity makes the system
hard to change, hard to evolve, hard to
extend. Modularity, the goal of
modularity is the opposite. Let's say
that you are building a system. Let's
say it works. It implements its current
functionalities, its business
requirements. Awesome. However, if that
system is being used by people tomorrow,
a week from now, a month from now,
doesn't matter how long it will take,
but they will ask for more features. So,
we will have to extend it. So, I would
say that the goal of modularity is to
extend the goals the system addresses.
It should not only address the goals
that are needed today, but it should
also make it easier to implement the
goals that might be required in the
future. And of course, what I mean here
is not implement all the functionalities
that might be requested in the future.
That's not possible. However, reasonable
changes that the users might request in
the future should be much clearer, much
easier to implement in the future
without having that sense of going
through a big bowl of mud. It should be
clear what you have to change and what
are the changes that you need to make to
implement those future goals, those
future business requirements. So, I
would say that we have two opposites. We
have complexity and we have modularity.
If you're looking at software design
decisions that we are making, each one
of them can either take our system
towards complexity or towards
modularity. Where should it go? Well,
probably we wanted to go towards
modularity and how we can do it.
Probably it has something to do with
coupling. Okay. And we'll explore that
more in a second. I'm curious for
listeners for whom these concepts are
new. Can you give some specific or maybe
just one specific example of what would
they expect to see? I think most people
can conceive in their mind of what a big
ball of mud could look like, right?
There's long methods everywhere or
there's just class explosion and there's
no sense of, you know, how things fit
together. Or maybe there's 50 different
Docker containers that have all kinds of
complex like, who knows? You could have
a distributed ball of mud. But that's
easy to conceive. I think it might be
harder for listeners to conceive of what
does a good modular system look like?
And adding on to that, what is a module?
Have modularity like it's a good thing,
but like what's a module? Can you give
some examples? Yeah, that's a great
question and again that's why not enough
ink has been spilled on this topic. I
mean we can go back 50 years to David
Parnos's paper on the criteria to be
used in decomposing systems into modules
but he doesn't even necessarily give a
definition that still holds up today. So
I'm curious what your thoughts are on
that. Yeah. So I will address the first
part of your question first and it's
what is that modularity? What is that
module design that we want to achieve?
So I would say that it all boils down to
two things. First, let's say that you
have a new business requirement that you
have to implement or maybe a change in
an existing one. You want to know
exactly what is the place in the system
that has to be changed in order to
implement that. That's the first part.
And the second one is when you are going
to make the change, you need a certain
level of confidence what's going to
happen following that change. Again, you
don't want those surprises in production
a month later. Right. Right. So, for me,
that's the goal of Majillari. It all
boils down to where to change and what
the effects of my change are going to be
on the rest of the system. I don't want
to be surprised. Okay. So, my experience
would be I know where to go to make a
given change as opposed to I guess the
counter example is it could be
everywhere and anywhere and who knows,
right? That's the complex system where
only after I take action can I see the
effects. But I guess can you give some
specific examples of I walk into a
codebase and it's modular. What am I
going to see? What am I going to
experience? How is it going to help
guide me to knowing where I should make?
And I'm sure it's different for
different languages and frameworks and
things like that. But maybe give
listeners some flavor of what they
should expect to see. And maybe there's
different levels of modularity that you
could discuss as well. What are the
kinds of things that they would expect
to see in that kind of a well-designed
system? Yeah. And that takes us to the
second part of your previous question
about what is a module. Ah yes, because
there are so much
misunderstandings about what a module
is. There are so many different
interpretations. One that is really
popular nowadays is that a module is a
logical boundary. A boundary within a
service or within a physical component.
For example, inn nets namespace in Java
it's package etc. And then there is this
definition of a component which is a
physical boundary. Here we have
boundaries of services of systems all
those deployable units. However,
however, I will ask you until the end of
this podcast to forget about these
definitions and instead I will do what
you suggested. I will rewind the time 50
years back and talk about how modules
were defined way back then when that
term modularity and modules were just
introduced to software engineering and
back then a module was defined by three
criteria. The first one is a module
should implement some welldefined
functionality. Which means if you're
looking at some boundary, you can
describe what is doing. What is the
functionality that is implemented within
that boundary. Second, that boundary
should expose a public interface through
which the rest of the system, its other
modules can execute that functionality.
So we have a public interface. That's
the second criterion. And finally, the
third one, and it's the most I would say
important one nowadays is that a module
should have a potential of being
independently compiled. The potential
should be there. Now, it doesn't mean
that we should compile it independently.
That means that if you are looking at a
service or a micros service, does it fit
that definition? Well, if you can
explain what is the functionality
implemented by that service, it has
public interface and it is already
independently compiled. Awesome. We can
say that this is a module. Now, if you
look into its internal structure and
let's say that it's implemented in C#
because I love C#. In C what you will
find there is a bunch of namespaces. Now
each namespace has a name and it has
some functionality that is implemented
within it. Can you describe it? Let's
say that the answer is yes. Awesome.
Does it have a public interface? It
does. Awesome. Can it be independently
compiled? Yes, it can. So we can call a
namespace a module as well. Within that
name space we'll find a bunch of objects
or classes. Each one of them has
functionality that is implemented. We
can describe it. Yes. It has public
interface. Yes. Can it be independently
compiled? Yes. Should it be? Depends.
But the potential is there. Is it there?
So a class or an object can also be
defined as a module. We can zoom in even
deeper. Let's say that we're looking at
a method within a class. Does it have a
well- definfined functionality? If it
does, awesome. Public interface, we have
that signature through which that method
can be called. Can it be independently
compiled? Well, in many languages, it
can. Probably it shouldn't, but you can
do it. So, even a method can be called a
module. So, what we are getting to is
that modules are fractal. There are
different levels of abstraction. We are
used to this term levels of abstraction
or layers of abstraction doesn't matter.
As Dyster famously said, the purpose of
an abstraction is to create a new
semantic level in which one can be
absolutely precise. So we have different
levels of abstraction with different
types of modules within each one of
those levels. Now going back to our
first topic of complexity. Each one of
the layers or levels of abstraction
manages
complexity. The level of detail of the
business domain or implementation
details that it uses in its definitions
in the definitions of its public
interfaces for example is going to be
different but the goal is there on all
the levels to manage complexity. So
going back to your previous question
about what should you expect? What are
those modules? So the answer is modules
can be found at different levels of
abstraction. All of them should manage
complexity in a fractal-like hierarchy.
So summarize again the three elements
that make up a module just to make sure
it hits home with listeners. Yeah. First
one is well-defined functionality. Can
you describe what a module is doing or
you are going to resort to for example
reading the implementation details? If
you have to read the implementation
details, you don't know what it's doing.
What you're describing is how it is
doing that. You're not describing what
it is doing. That's the first point.
That's a good clarification too, right?
Because that kind of means in a way it's
a black box. It's something that I can
describe what it's going to do without
necessarily needing to know the details
of how. Yeah. Exly. That's number one.
Okay. Yeah, going back to that wonderful
book, philosophy of software design that
you mentioned in the introduction. I
love how the author defines what makes a
good module. A one that compresses all
the knowledge about the implementation
details into a short and easy to express
way of saying what that module is doing.
What is the function of it? What is the
functionality that it implements? as
opposed to for example as I mentioned
having to read the implementation
details or maybe you will say that this
module is doing that and that and that
and that and that and a bunch of
unrelated things that's also problematic
that goes against the definition of a
module it's actually helpful you bring
up John Osterhout who wrote that book
and just to give listeners a visual
picture in their minds of what you're
describing he talks about deep versus
shallow modules and this is going to
relate to the second piece of the
definition that you gave for modularity.
So you can envision in your head a very
wide rectangle that's very shallow and
it has a lot of connectors on top. That
would be a shallow module that doesn't
provide a lot of functionality and it
exposes a lot of its internal details
through a very broad API right with
maybe lots of methods or lots of
interfaces or whatever it might be. A
deep module is going to be more like a
vertical rectangle with a shallow
surface with few connectors but it's
going to have rich and deep
functionality below it. And I think that
helps guide into that second piece of a
module you talked about which is a
public interface. And while public
interface is the important part of that
second part of the definition, I think
another important part is what does that
public interface look like? Because it
may be more or less helpful depending on
how well it aligns with what Dr.
Osterhow talks about in his book. Yeah.
So here I have to resort to the default
answer. It depends. Yes. Okay. It
depends on the level of abstraction you
want. Software architects. Yes. Yeah. If
you're working with let's say services
or microservices then the interface is
going to be let's say a web API rest API
or the events or messages that are
consumed or published by that service
synchronously or asynchronously all the
way it interacts with its environment.
If you are on the other end of the
spectrum, let's say that you're looking
at a method, then the method signature
is its interface. That's how external
components or external methods or
modules can execute its functionality.
It can be private, locked in within its
object or it can be public. It depends.
But it has to provide a convenient, easy
to understand and well-defined way to
execute its functionality. Whoever needs
that functionality shouldn't be reading
through its implementation details to
figure out how to use it. Right? That's
the goal. Okay. So, we've revisited the
first two components of the definition
of modularity. And what was the third
again? Yeah. And the third component or
property that a module should have is
that potential of being independently
compiled. Now, why it's important? Well,
the potential should be there. If it's
not there, it means that that component
that you're looking at, that potential
module is not really a module. It cannot
be compiled, deployed, tested
independently of some other things. So
probably they should be treated as one
boundary, as one module. That's why that
third criteria is important here, the
potential of being independently
compiled. And would that be partially
because if it can't be independently
compiled that there's some form of
coupling that maybe we need to be
addressing that we've maybe missed.
Yeah, there is something that forces you
to always work on those two I don't want
to say modules let's say two components
together at all times. Okay, great. So I
have in my mind this spectrum on one end
I've got complexity which according to
your definition is things that I can't
know the effects until I've taken an
action and then observe the outcome as
opposed to things where someone may know
what's going to happen or I know it
because it's clear and obvious right so
that's complexity and then on the other
end of the spectrum I have modularity
and I wonder if other authors or other
people have different perspective like
is modularity the only way to deal with
complexity or what are your thoughts on
that. Yeah. So, look, my thoughts are
based on my experience, right? Mhm.
Experience that was tested in the
battlefield and my experience says that
yes, that's the only way that's the only
way that works. Now, when I am
presenting on this topic, sometimes
people do disagree with me about when
I'm saying a design decision can either
take you towards complexity or towards
majority. And people say that no, a
system can be both. It can be modular in
some places and it can be complex in
some areas and that's correct. However,
however, if you're making a design
decision, let's say that you're
introducing a new module, a new
boundary, a new method, new interface,
etc. I still claim that that decision
can either take you towards complexity
or towards modularity. Yes, this the
overarching system can be both. It can
be complex. It can be modular at the
same time because some of its parts are
designed in different ways. That's true
of course. However, if you're looking on
that level of design decisions, I would
say that either complexity or
modularity. And I think that makes sense
because to extend your thought there a
little bit, I could have an
implementation that's complex, but if
the public interface is simple and hides
the integrator from that complexity,
then that's kind of where there could be
that dance between the system having
both complex parts and modular parts. Is
that kind of what you're implying there?
Yeah, absolutely. As Eric Evans said,
not all of a large system will ever be
welldesigned. There will be parts that
are not business critical, that are not
mission critical that yeah, it's okay to
round corners there. How to identify
those areas? I hope we'll get to this
topic in this podcast. Yeah, we'll
definitely want to get there. And can
you provide a real world example maybe
of what would be the problem? Say if I
tried to perfectly design every single
aspect of something in the real world,
what would be the impact of that instead
of maybe cutting some corners here and
there? Yeah. Well, what's going to
happen is if you're a startup company,
well, you're not going to deploy
anything. Uhhuh. As a startup, what you
want to do is to address complexity in
the business domain. That essential
complexity. Let's say you're a startup
company and you want to provide a
solution for your customers, people that
you hope are going to be your customers.
So, you want to solve one of their
problems. You hope that you understand
what is the problem that they need help
with and you hope that your solution is
going to address that problem. Will it
the only way to know is sorry that's
complexity if that would be easy
everyone would be doing it. So you have
to do it and to observe the outcome
that's complexity in the business domain
and to get that feedback yeah you need
to cut corners. If you're not going to
do it your competitors will and they
will get to market much faster than you
are. So, we have to balance our desire
to build beautiful systems that are
well-designed and modular and you know
the real world where
sometimes it pays to cut corners. Well,
and I think of even like a construction
project sitting here in my home and you
in your home. I imagine that there are
some tolerances about just how close say
the stick framing in my wall is. And if
somebody was so precise down to the
millimeter, that would have increased
the cost. it would have, you know,
slowed things down. It would have been
way overdone. Instead, we just cover
over with sheetrock and we move on,
right? And we're like, it's good enough.
It does the job and it solves the
problem of structure. So, it doesn't
need to be designed to that perfect
level of detail, right? Yeah. Well,
don't get me started on my home because
so many corners were cut here. Oh, yes.
You can't cut too many corners, which we
want to avoid. But let's not go there.
You can go back listeners. I mentioned
at the top of the show, Steve Smith on
software quality. We, you know, we can
revisit that one. But in the meantime,
let's go back to coupling, which of
course is, you know, the hallmark and
the highlight of your book. So, as the
book continues, you take some previous
models, you know, we talked about
previous ink that was spilled, right?
You take some previous models for
identifying coupling, which it'd be
great if you can, you know, say what
those are if listeners are interested in
going back and seeing the history of
this conversation all the way back to
Yordon and Parnos and all of these
different people from way back in the
day. So, there have been models for
identifying coupling and you've come up
with a new approach. So what issues did
you see in the previous models and how
is yours different? Yeah. So first of
all why coupling? Well once we have
those opposing properties something that
can be either complex or modular then
there is something in the middle that is
shared by both of those properties.
Something that if we learn to control
then we are going to control the
outcome. And in my opinion that's
coupling. That's how we're going to
design coupling. So what is coupling? In
simple words, if two things are coupled,
it means that they're connected. If you
have one method calling another one,
they're coupled. There is a connection
there. Two objects, same thing. Two
services, if they are integrated one way
or another, they're coupled. So first of
all, coupling is not something that we
can eliminate from our design. Like that
slogan of let's decouple everything.
Well, you can do it, but you're not
going to build any system without those
integrations, without those connections.
So, we need that coupling. So, we cannot
eliminate coupling. What we should do is
to look at it and to understand how
those connections can be designed. What
are those design decisions we can make
about those connections and how they're
going to affect that overarching system
and our stress levels in the future when
we will have to change them. And the
first thing that we should look at is
knowledge. Let's say that we have two
modules that are integrated with each
other. Doesn't matter what those modules
are at this point. Let's say that
anything on any level of abstraction
doesn't matter. They can be two methods.
They can be two services, two systems,
whatever. In order to work together,
they have to know something about each
other. At the minimum, they have to know
what is the functionality that is
implemented by the module that I want to
call that I want to execute. Right? Or
maybe when I am using its public
interface, by using that public
interface, I'm getting some knowledge
about its internal structure. For
example, what is the model of the
business domain that is being used there
in Turkey? Or maybe there is no public
interface at all or maybe it's there but
you know I decided that I have a smarter
way of integrating like going straight
to the implementation details and using
them for integration. Let's say that
both of us are implementing
microservices and as we all know
microservices should be integrated
through public interfaces their APIs.
say okay Jeff your public interface is
amazing however give me your database I
will take whatever I need and make some
changes there and that's it right if
only no one would ever do that but it it
happens all the time yeah yeah so that
part of knowledge that is being
exchanged whenever we have multiple
modules that are integrated that
knowledge can be knowledge of public
interfaces of integration contracts or
it can spill some knowledge about its
internal structure, the knowledge about
the functionality that is implemented by
a service. By the way, let's say that we
have two services that are not
integrated. In anyway, we have a system
with two components that are not
integrated, not aware of each other at
all. However, they implement the same
business rule or the same business
algorithm. So, we have that knowledge of
the business domain that is duplicated
in both components, in both modules.
Let's say that they're integrated
wirelessly or something. That knowledge
is duplicated and there is no explicit
interface through which that knowledge
flows. When that knowledge will change
well guess what one of them is going to
be changed for sure. The second one the
question is when it's going to be
changed. So yeah that's the first aspect
of coupling. What is the extent of
knowledge that is being exchanged across
coupled components across integrated
components? the more knowledge we are
going to exchange well the more
cascading changes will follow. If we
minimize the knowledge we are minimizing
cascading changes. If on the other hand
we are maximizing the knowledge well
we're maximizing cascading changes.
Going back to the example of two
microservices tomorrow you're going to
change the schema of that table that
your micros service manages and I'm
using it as you know impolite way let's
define it that
way in a sense I am introducing
dependence on your implementation detail
as if I'm saying okay whatever you're
going to change in your implementation
details it has that huge potential of
causing cascade ing changes in my
service. So you make a change, best case
scenario, you tell me that you made a
change, you shouldn't do it. So instead,
you're going to deploy your changes and
then suddenly my service stops working
in production. I have sleepless night
and then I find out okay that table
schema was changed. So yeah, let's
introduce a corresponding change in my
service. So that part is knowledge. Now
going back to her question about the
history of that notion of coupling and
how it was introduced to software
engineering. So there is this
methodology called structured design.
They started working on it in late60s.
First books were published in early 70s
and it was like a domain driven design
in those days and that methodology
introduced a way to evaluate coupling.
The model that was introduced back then
was called module coupling. It had six
levels and those levels were defined
following programming languages that
were popular back then like cobalt,
fortrun and other fun stuff that we are
not really familiar with nowadays and
let's be honest we don't want to be
familiar with nowadays. So it had levels
like data coupling, stem coupling,
control coupling, external common and
all the way to content coupling. Now
these levels basically describe what I
just said. Those different types of
knowledge that can be exchanged across
boundaries of modules. The problem with
that approach nowadays, not back then.
I'm not saying that that approach is
bad. No, it was awesome. However,
nowadays it's really hard to use it
because first of all, people are not
familiar with Fortun. People are so
lucky nowadays, right? So in order to
understand what's the difference between
common coupling and external coupling
they have to understand what these
keywords and those languages mean.
That's problematic. It also had six
levels and some of them kind of
described same things. However, because
of the ways those programming languages
were defined they had to have separate
levels. Now nowadays we don't really
need that. That's why in my book I
introduced a different model that is
called integration strength. That
integration strength has only four
levels. Basically these four levels
simply adapt those six levels from
structured design and make them way
easier to understand nowadays to
remember them and to use them. So
instead of data coupling, what I'm
saying is contract coupling. If all your
modules know about each other is
integration contracts, awesome. That's a
contract coupling. These would be the
public interfaces and the public data
contracts exposed by those interfaces.
Correct. Yeah. Exactly. Yeah. Stamp
coupling. It's basically about models.
Let's say that you have a model of a
business domain that that is used in
your service and you're exposing that
model. Cool. Whenever you will change or
whenever you will have to evolve that
model well as long as it's exposed
across the boundary that change is going
to affect whoever is using that public
interface. So instead of stamp coupling
let's call it model coupling we have
that model that knowledge of a model
that is being exposed across the
boundaries. Next we have control
external and common coupling which can
be called functional coupling in our
world because basically what they are
describing is knowledge of functional
requirements the functionality that is
being implemented by the modules. And
then we have content coupling in a
structure design which is basically
about introducing a dependencies on
implementation details. Instead of
working with public interfaces, you
integrate through use of private
interfaces or other implementation
details. So let's call it intrusive
coupling. It's going to be easier to
understand and easier to use. So overall
we have four types of knowledge.
Knowledge of integration interfaces,
contract coupling, model coupling,
functional coupling and intrusive
coupling. Four levels. So that was the
model that was introduced in ' 70s. Now
in '90s a different model for evaluating
coupling was introduced by Miller P.
Jones and it is called canence and this
one is way more detailed. It provides a
more granular types of knowledge that
can be exchanged across boundaries of
objects. This model was oriented to more
towards object-oriented programming
paradigm. Now which one is better
structured designs, module coupling or
conacance? Well, there's no point in
trying to draw parallels between them
like what this level in structure design
means in canance or which one is better,
which one should I learn? It makes no
sense because they're describing
different things. Structure designs
module coupling and as a result
integration strength describes types of
interfaces. What is the type of
knowledge that is being exchanged? It's
important because well, as we're going
to discuss, it's important to evaluate
the amount the amount of knowledge that
is being exchanged exposed across the
boundaries. How we're going to evaluate
it, how we're going to weigh like what
are the units, kilograms or what pounds?
We don't know how to do it right now. So
instead, we can differentiate between
different types of knowledge. If we have
model coupling, we know that it shares
more knowledge than construct coupling.
and less knowledge than functional
coupling or intrusive coupling. Now,
canence can still be very useful for
looking deeper into the complexity of
that knowledge within that each type of
those interfaces. So in my model in
integration strength I am using those
adapted terms from structure design to
differentiate between four types of
technologies and within each one of them
you can evaluate the degree degree of
each level and you do it by using a
subset of the model called canence. So
in a sense we had those two models. We
had module coupling 70s then we had
conacance 90s and now we have in
aggression strength that kind of
combines them and adapts them to our
world makes it easier to use them. So
you've summarized for us how those
previous models of defining coupling
have been brought together and
simplified with your model as it relates
to knowledge sharing or or what you call
integration strength. Is there another
aspect to coupling that you describe
that can help people to sort of conceive
of how to design their systems and
manage coupling? Yeah, absolutely. So
that aspect of knowledge sharing or
integration strength is only one
dimension, one of three of the ways
coupling affects your design. The second
one is the dimension of space. So you
are sharing knowledge. Is it good or
bad? We don't know because it depends on
other factors. One of them is that
physical distance through which that
knowledge travels. Let's say that we
have two modules sharing knowledge about
their functional requirements. So we
have that functional coupling between
them. Is it good or bad? Well, it
depends on the distance. Let's say that
those modules are
microservices. So we are sharing quite a
lot of knowledge between them. That
means there are going to be quite a lot
of cascading changes. Is it good or bad?
Probably not something that I want in my
design. So, it's not going to be good.
On the other hand, let's say that those
two modules are located close to each
other. Let's say that those are two
classes within the same name space and
they have to share that knowledge.
There's no other way to implement them
because that's how that system is
defined by its business requirements. In
that case, well, yes, there are share
knowledge. Yes, there will be cascading
changes. However, they're close to each
other. So, when those changes are going
to happen, that cognitive load that I'm
going to experience is not going to be
that high as if I have to modify two
microservices simultaneously. No, they
are located close to each other within
the same probably the same folder, maybe
even the same file. So, I know that I
have to change those two things. They're
located close to each other. that change
is going to be something that is pretty
obvious how to make it and what its
effects are going to be. Right? So we
have that dimension of space that
distance through which that knowledge
has to travel to reach its destination.
Now once we have those two dimensions we
can already talk about interesting
combinations of two values. Let's say
that we are
minimizing the knowledge that is shared
across the boundaries. So we are
limiting ourselves to sharing only the
knowledge of integration contracts and
that's it without spilling any details
up about how our modules are implemented
internally. In that case, if we maximize
the distance between them, what we get
is a system with modules with quite an
extensive distance between them. And
it's okay because they're not going to
have to change together. We're
minimizing those cascading changes by
minimizing the knowledge. Great. Now,
what if, as I mentioned a minute ago,
what if we cannot minimize that
knowledge? Sometimes we do have to share
on that knowledge of functional
requirements or we have to use the same
model of the business domain or maybe
even implementation details. Who knows?
Sometimes we can find ourselves in those
situations. So let's assume that we are
sharing lots of knowledge. In this case,
what we can do to manage the cognitive
load that we will experience in the
future is to bring them close to each
other. If we do that, we have high
amount of knowledge, low distance. In
other words, this relationship describes
high cohesion. We have things that will
change together. They have to change
together because of those business
requirements. There's no other way
around it. So, we're making our lives,
our future lives better by bringing them
close to each other. So, that will when
we'll have to change them together, they
will be close to each other. it will be
easier for us to implement that change.
So again that first relationship low
knowledge high distance is this is what
we usually call low scapling the
opposite one high amount of knowledge
low distance is high
cohesion now what if we'll have both of
them both of those properties or those
dimensions have high values let's say we
have high amount of knowledge shared
across high distance well guess what is
going to happen in your future those two
modules will change together whenever
there is a change in the business
requirements and each of those changes
will have to propagate across the whole
system towards other components that are
integrated with it. So we will have to
chase those distant component distant
modules all over the place and to modify
them together forget about some of them
discovered in production etc. all the
fun stuff about living with a big bowl
of money, you know. So that's
complexity. The cognitive load that you
will go through to evolve that system in
the future is going to be insane. That's
complexity. Now a bit counterintuitive
relationship is the opposite one. Let's
say that they have two modules or a
number of modules. They're not sharing
much out. Let's say it's either the
lowest level contract coupling or maybe
they're not even integrated with each
other. So that shared knowledge is zero
basically. And I'm going to put them
close to each other. So both aspects the
integration strength the shared
knowledge is minimized and the distance
between them is minimized as well. And
when I'm doing conference talks on this
topic I usually ask the audience. So
let's vote who thinks this is a good
design who thinks it's a bad design. And
usually it's a draw. It's 50/50. Yeah.
Well, in my mind right now, I have like
a utils or a helpers project in my mind
where it's like a grab bag of
everything. Is that is that kind of what
you're saying? Yeah. You know what?
Let's get back to the that topic of
utils and helper in a few minutes. Okay,
great. For now, let's talk about more of
business critical stuff. Okay, let's say
business functionality. Great. Business
objects not related to each other. M and
we put them close to each other. Is this
good or bad? So on the one hand, it
sounds okayish because yeah, they're not
going to change together. We're
minimizing the knowledge. Great.
However, that's a tricky question
because if we only have two modules,
then let's be honest, who cares? But in
a real project, those things are not
limited to one or two. They are rather
growing towards infinity. So let's say
you have dozen or maybe a hundred of
unrelated modules located close to each
other. The distance between them is low.
They're not going to change together.
But your future self will have to change
one of them in the future, right? And
when we were talking about the goal of
modularity that it should be easy to
understand where the thing you want to
change is located. Suddenly we are
getting back to that cognitive load
because now you're looking at that bunch
of things that are shoehorned into the
same boundary and you have to find the
one that you have to modify. So again we
have cognitive load. So again we have
complexity. So this relationship when
both values are
low introduces complexity as well. So
overall if you're looking at integration
strength and distance if they have
opposing values one is high the second
one is low that design takes you towards
modularity if their values are equal
let's say both are high or both are low
that design takes you towards
complexity and you know what let's talk
about the third dimension and the third
dimension is the dimension of time so
the first one was strength that
gravitational
pull when components have towards each
other. The second one is the dimension
of space the distance through which
knowledge has to go and the third one is
the dimension of time. Now why this one
is important? Let's say that I have two
modules with intrusive coupling between
them and these two modules are two
systems. That means we have quite a high
distance between them and we also have
quite a lot of knowledge shared between
them because of intrusive coupling.
That's another tricky question I love to
ask at conferences. Is this design
necessarily good or bad? It depends.
Sure. Of
course. Yeah. So, let's talk about what
it depends on. So, let's say that that's
the way I'm designing the interactions
between my business objects in part of a
system that implements some business
critical functionality. Well, that's
bad, right? However, on the other hand,
let's say that we have a legacy system.
And you know how legacy systems work?
They work. How? Nobody knows. They just
work. They're not going to change
because nobody has that courage of
touching them. But sometimes you do need
to interact with them. You need to take
some information, maybe some data from
those systems. Well, if that system is
defined as legacy and it's not going to
change, then well, I don't care. I can
introduce that intrusive coupling. I
will go straight to its database and
take whatever I need, right? M because
nobody is going to change that schema
and that takes us to that dimension of
time or volatility how frequently our
components are expected to change. If
we're talking about something like a
legacy system or like that utils
namespace or those helper objects that
are just a bunch of string related
operations that are not really going to
change that frequently hopefully it's
okay to tolerate some complexity by
putting them together. It's okay to
introduce that intrusive coupling to a
legacy system because of low volatility.
Now how can we evaluate volatility? How
can we
analyze that system and make that
decision that yeah it's okay here we are
not expecting much of changes. Well
there are different ways we can do it.
There are different models of predicting
the future. The one that I prefer as a
domain driven design fanboy is domain
driven designs subdomains. Basically the
says that if you're looking at any
business domain, you can identify three
types of business subdomains. You will
find core subdomains that are describing
some core business functionality.
Something that is business critical. If
you make a mistake there, well, troubles
are going to follow. And the opposite of
a core subdomain is a supporting
subdomain. Supporting subdomain, it's
something that you have to implement,
but it's not business critical. It's
something that let's say you need some
crowd data entry screen. It's boring,
right? Implementing it's not
interesting. It's obvious how to
implement. There is no complexity in
that business domain and business is not
really interested in evolving its
functionality in the future. Like it's
not going to affect the company's bottom
line in any way. So if we are comparing
those two already core subdomain and
sporting subdomain core is going to
change much more frequently because it's
all about that competitive advantage of
the company and the business is
interested in optimizing it over time.
So there will be much more changes in
core subdomains than in supporting
subdomains. The third type of subdomains
is generic subdomains. And if previous
two we have to implement them ourselves.
Generic subdomains are something that
somebody has already implemented for us.
It's all those areas, those complex
problems that it's not worth trying to
solve yourself. You just use some
product that implements that
functionality and your competitors are
going to use it and nobody cares and
it's not going to affect your bottom
line in any way. So those are generic
subdomains. That generic solution that
you are using will it change? It might
change. That implementation within the
boundary of a generic subdomain might
change. Maybe there will be security
fixes or new versions etc. So there will
be some volatility there but that's a
solved problem. So we are not really
interested in trying to solve it. We are
looking more at core subdomains and
supporting subdomains. One is
interesting problem. The second one is
boring problem. Interesting problem is
going to change way more frequently than
the boring problem. supporting
subdomain. So that's the model that I
prefer to use to evaluate volatility
levels. Now in the book I go much deeper
into other things that can also affect
volatility because poor design can make
your supporting subdomain quite
volatile. If for example you have a
supporting subdomain business- wise it
shouldn't change that frequently. Can
you give an example of a supporting
domain that might fit this concept?
Let's say that you're implementing a
marketing company that offers an
innovative way of optimizing advertising
campaigns to make them as profitable as
possible to show the ads in the most
effective way on the cheapest ad spaces
etc. For that system, its core
subdomains are going to be all about
that optimizations, right? However, you
still have to manage your advertising
materials like those banners you're
going to show or those landing pages. So
you need some crap data entry screen for
that creative catalog. Is that
interesting? No. If I'll design it
better, will it make the company more
profitable? Will it make it easier to
optimize advertising campaigns? No. So
that creative catalog is going to be a
supporting subdomain. Whereas
optimizations that service that the
company is providing or it is promising
to provide to its customers, it's much
more about its core subdomains.
So we've explored these three different
dimensions of coupling. You've talked
about integration strength which is
measured in how much knowledge two
modules share. We've got distance which
is the amount of sort of space we can
kind of think of it that way between
these different modules. And then we've
talked about volatility or how subject
something is to changing over time. Now,
if you can kind of bring that all
together for listeners because you know
it's a lot I think in an auditory format
to kind of hold together and of course
you know get the book, read the book,
right? All that that's all great but you
know can you bring it all together for
listeners here as we come to the end of
this episode. Yeah. So first of all if
we're looking at integration strength
and distance if we put exor explicive or
between them then we can express
complexity and modularity. Modularity is
strength exclusive or distance. If the
values are different, great. You have
modularity. They're equal. You have
complexity. As we mentioned in the
introduction or in the first part of
this podcast, sometimes it's okay to
round corner. Sometimes it's okay to
introduce complexity. So we can extend
that formula and we'll put that
relationship between strength and
distance in parenthesis and say
modularity or not volatility. Which
means if volatility is low it's okay to
have complexity to have both strength
and distance to be either high or either
low. However, if volatility is high,
then make sure that one of them is high
either strength or distance and one of
them is low because then what you're
doing is you're helping your future self
to find that place you have to change
and you're helping yourself to predict
what the outcome of that change is going
to be. I appreciate a couple times that
that's come up, cognitive load and the
idea of not hating your future self. So,
that's great. Is there anything else you
would hope listeners would take away
from this episode or any closing
thoughts? Well, I would say that
coupling
is way too important. Any design
decision that we're making, it doesn't
matter what is the level of abstraction
we are working on. It doesn't matter
what is the type of component we're
working on or what is the language we
are using. Even if you're looking at
something that some people might not
consider a programming language like
HTML, I would say that strength and
distance are there as well. So whether
you're going to read my book or a
different book, I would say make sure
you understand how coupling affects your
systems and how it affects the cognitive
load your future self is going to
experience. If listeners want to learn
more, where can they go or what should
they do? Yeah. So I spent over five
years writing that book balancing
coupling in software design. Put my soul
into it. I think everything I know we
try to condense it into those 300 pages.
Yeah. They can follow me on Twitter on
blue sky. My handle is
VladicK. My blog is ladic.com which is
kind of not really alive lately but you
can go update it before we publish the
episode.
Let's be honest, I'm not going to do it.
Okay. Okay. All right. That's fine.
Well, Vlad, thank you so much for
joining me on the show. Thank you so
much, Jeff, for having me. It's a
pleasure and an honor being here. This
is Jeff Doolittle for Software
Engineering Radio. Thanks for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by E
Software Magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
[Music]
seradio.slack.com. You can also email us
at
teamse-radio.net. This and all other
episodes of SE Radio is licensed under
Creative Common License 2.5. Thanks for
listening.